<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore mans appeale In a sermon preached at Leicester assises before the judges. By T.P.</title>
            <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836576</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836576</idno>
            <idno type="VID">857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1526:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore mans appeale In a sermon preached at Leicester assises before the judges. By T.P.</title>
                  <author>Pestell, Thomas, 1584?-1659?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw: Griffin, for Arthur Johnson, and are to be sold at his shop neere the great north doore of St. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.P. = Thomas Pestell.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 409) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:857:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POORE MANS APPEALE.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preached at <hi>Leiceſter</hi> Aſsiſes
<hi>before the Iudges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO. 22.22.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Rob not the Poore, becauſe hee is poore; neither oppreſſe the afflicted in the gate: For the Lord will plead their cauſe, and ſpoyle the ſoule of thoſe that ſpoyle him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Edw: Griffin,</hi> for
<hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere the great North doore of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:857:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:857:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Sir HENRY HOBART, <hi>Knight and Baronet, Lord</hi> chiefe Iuſtice of his Maieſties <hi>Court of Common Pleas, and</hi> Chauncellor to the moſt <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince</hi> CHARLES, Prince of WALES, Grace and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat reuerend Regard your Honor gaue this Sermon, when it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered you, as a meſſage from the Higheſt, was but a iuſt Regard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But for your vouchſafing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, and giue the frame thereof approbation, both it and I haue therein largely taſted of your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Regard. Both your Regards it then had, and I now in regard of both, conceiued an hope that the publike inſcribing it thus to your Lordſhips name, would paſſe, at leaſt for a pardonable tranſgresſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and might (peraduenture) in the nobleneſſe of <pb facs="tcp:857:3"/>your interpretation be accepted, (as I intend it) for an act of my dutifull regard to your Honor. Whereof how can I forbeare preſumption, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring who hath ſaid; <hi>Yee are Gods, and are all children of the moſt High.</hi> Your Lordſhip then cannot vnreſemble your heauenly Father, who gently takes the meaneſt oblations of the pooreſt and loweſt, being himſelfe rich ouer all, and
<hi>Higher then the higheſt.</hi> He, <hi>the Iudge of all;</hi> The Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of Heauen and Earth, bleſſe and direct you ſo, as we may long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, from him, thorough you the beames and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his Iuſtice in earth, and you, after this life iuſtly finiſht, the bright beames of his Glorie, and that bleſſed Regard, and reward of his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Mercie in the higheſt Heauen; So prayes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips true honourer, <hi>T. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:857:3"/>
            <head>THE POORE MANS <hi>APPEALE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLESIASTES 5.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If in a Countrie thou ſeeſt the oppresſion of the poore, and the defrauding of Iuſtice and Iudgement; Bee not aſtonied at the matter; <hi>For he</hi> that is higher then the higheſt regardeth, and there bee higher then they.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall haue ſome vſe of the whole verſe, but theſe words, <hi>(For hee that is higher then the higheſt, regardeth.)</hi> I chooſe forth for the Text, as being <hi>axis</hi> and <hi>Cardo,</hi> the hindge vpon which all turnes; For they are a reaſon of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the ſubſtance of the latter. Their parts are viſible; two perſons, and an action. Firſt, the perſons, <hi>Altus deſuper altum, &amp;c.</hi> or
<hi>Altus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Alto,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Tremelius.</hi>) Two perſons then,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and two titles, high ones both, yet largely differing: Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior <pb n="2" facs="tcp:857:4"/>ſtands betwixt them here like an
<hi>Iſtmus,</hi> or <hi>Hiatus</hi> rather, large in extent, as the ſpace betwixt earth and heauen. <hi>For thou couldſt haue none</hi> (ſayes Chriſt to <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi>) not the loweſt degree, <hi>except it were giuen thee</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuper, <hi>from aboue.</hi> So that the one depends of the other; the one abſolute, and in <hi>recto: Altus</hi> the high one by way of excellence; the other in <hi>obliquo,</hi> and with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to a Superiour:
<hi>Alto</hi> an high one too, but not like <hi>Altus,</hi> no, the caſe is altered; <hi>Alius</hi> is <hi>primus</hi> and <hi>ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miu,</hi> the firſt, the chiefeſt high one, comes therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Superior, as hauing none, but
<hi>Alto</hi> is ſet after, and would ſoone come all to nothing, if not gouerned by Superior here: So much, and ſo iuſtly is <hi>Altus</hi> ſuperior <hi>Alto.</hi> In ſumme, the latter of theſe titles belongs to men; that is plaine by the addition here, or reddition rather; For it is the ſame againe another way. And there be higher then they: then who? then thoſe men ſpoken of before. But for the firſt title here it does, it can belong to none but God. He onely is the high one, or that high one: It is a peculiar of his, and his prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue onely. So <hi>Dauid, Thou whoſe name is Iehovah, thou alone art moſt high ouer all.</hi> Pſal. 83. <hi>vlt.</hi> And that <hi>Solomon</hi> here intends this onely high God, is apparent too, in the laſt ſtraine of the verſe; where he names him <hi>Alti,</hi> in the plurall, which tho ſome interpret of God, and his Angels, yet <hi>Iunius</hi> better of God alone, excuſing the difference of number, partly by the ſacred myſterie of three perſons in the God-head, and partly by an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiſme, expreſſing by the poſitiue plurall a ſingular ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatiue, ſo rayſing the title from <hi>Altus</hi> to
<hi>Altiſſimus,</hi> or as the engliſh here, <hi>higher then the higheſt.</hi> So high in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that all words forſake vs in the vtterance; But of that when we trie this Title. We know now the perſons; The action remaines, and is aſcribed to <hi>Altiſſimus. God regards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> How meanes he? what does he regard? It is left here indefinite, <hi>Regards,</hi> and no more, but may be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:857:4"/>diuerſly vnderſtood, firſt by making this indefinite and vniuerſall too, the ſame with <hi>Heſiods</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſees all things, and <hi>Dauids, Quo fugiam?</hi> Whither ſhall I goe from thy preſence? And ſo his regard is the ſame with prouidence: or diuide this Sea into two armes of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iuſtice, acts of his ſpeciall prouidence ouer all men and all their actions; or apply it laſtly to this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in the text, and wee ſhall finde that God in both theſe hands of mercie and iuſtice takes, and with both theſe eyes beholds oppreſſion. Oppreſſion? why? is that the matter here? yes. <hi>If thou ſeeſt oppreſſion, bee not aſtoniſhed; for hee that is, &amp;c.</hi> It is true, hee mentions heere <hi>rapinam</hi> too, ſtealth or defrauding of iuſtice, but vpon the point it comes all to one: for bee it violence, or be it cunning, by fraud or by force, it forces not; it is oppreſſion: that is the Ocean which deuoures, and the common ſinke that ſwallowes both theſe flouds of wickedneſſe, both theſe filthy channels of corruption: But oppreſſion is an action, and <hi>actio eſt vis illata;</hi> ſo is oppreſſion right, and does inferre a paſſion; wee muſt haue a patient then, and we muſt finde out the agent: for if oppreſſion be obſerued, if God regard it, hee can not but regard them. Theſe in reaſon are like Plaintiffe and defendant in law, which is grounded on reaſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe would be brought in then before we can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede with our action: The Law will allow the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe firſt; cal him we need not; If thou ſeeſt the oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Poore. Hee's <hi>adeſt,</hi> there he is; <hi>the Poore,</hi> Alas poore man, poore and oppreſt too, thats an heauy caſe: who is there to ſpeak for him? not any man, no; for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regards him: the poore is deſpiſed of his own neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: heere he ſeemes to ſtand poore ſilly ſoule, with a face couered ouer with teares, his very heart broken his tongue cleaues to his roofe; onely his hands and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyes are lift vp towards heauen: I, there is his refuge, there is one that vnderſtands the language of his ſighs, and bends an eare to the voyce of his weeping, and <pb n="4" facs="tcp:857:5"/>though the high ones of the world turne away their eyes, yet hee that is higher then the higheſt regardeth: But where is the agent and defendant? wee ſhall need a queſt of inquiry for him: <hi>If thou ſeeſt, &amp;c. Non est in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentus:</hi> what, does hee ſlie for it? ſo much the worſe: But tis not poſſible he ſhould bee farre; the very ſinne will finde him out without a Cryer, tis a crying ſinne: Sure hee is hidden heere, this greedy eating <hi>Adam</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the leaues, or like <hi>Saul</hi> among the ſtuffe of the Text. Let vs turne it ouer againe: <hi>If thou ſeeſt the oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Poore,</hi> ſoft, <hi>the Poore oppreſt;</hi> who can this bee? and <hi>defrauding of iustice and iudgement,</hi> in whoſe power is it to doe that <hi>hee that is higher then the higheſt.</hi> There is all the perſons this Text affords.</p>
            <p>It is betwixt theſe two then; either the high one of heauen, or the high one of earth hath done this. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee the firſt, alas no; God oppreſſe the Poore? hee is their helper and defender, tis hee that regards him: or does God vſe to defraud in iudgement or iuſtice? Oh no, <hi>Shall not the Iudge of all the world doe according to right?</hi> yes, <hi>With righteouſneſſe ſhall he iudge the earth, and the people with equity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the other high one then, it can be none but he: hee is the Oppreſſor, whether it be an height of wealth, this, and ſo liker to fall vpon the poore <hi>è diametro,</hi> or an height of authority, and ſo apter to defraud in iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice; and whether this oppreſsion bee by violence or ſecret coſenage it skils not; they are both like to abide it; for God can abide neither of them both: but abhorres both the blood-thirſty and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull man. <hi>Pſ</hi> 5.6. Yet ſince the principall intended heere by <hi>Salomon,</hi> is the high one that abuſes his height of place and power to the oppreſſing of the poore: ſuch as theſe, if thou ſeeſt them doe ſo and ſo, and goe cleare away with it, yet bee not aſtoniſh'd, let not this ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thee; for <hi>hee that is higher then the higheſt regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:857:5"/>
            <p>Out of this text thus opened, ariſe theſe doctrinall concluſions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And firſt from the perſons. Firſt, that there bee high ones vpon earth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that theſe are ſometimes oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that God is ſtill the higheſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> From the action then. Firſt, God
<hi>regards,</hi> does marke and obſerue all things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, obſerues men and their actions with a double
<hi>Reſpice,</hi> a twofold obſeruat, of mercy to the good, iuſtice to the bad.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, hee both wayes regards oppreſſion, the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in mercy, becauſe <hi>pauperem</hi> firſt, and then <hi>paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem preſſum,</hi> the poore oppreſſed: The agent in iuſtice, becauſe
<hi>altum</hi> firſt, and then <hi>altum oppreſſorem,</hi> the high Oppreſſor. Of theſe in order, and order requires wee begin with the latter perſon firſt, and from it the firſt obſeruation is the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that there be ſuch, or there are higher powers. Height of wealth I paſſe ouer, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on dignitie.</p>
            <p>Height is by aſcending; aſſents are by ſtaires and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſuch aſconding is motion properly, all motion from ſome principle and euer to ſome end: The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall end of motion is
<hi>quies,</hi> peace and reſt, that is the end of this motion, wherein men aſcending are heighthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by degrees; Peace oppoſed both to warre and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order. This height is in differently called Magiſtracie: Magiſtracy I mean ſubordinate is either Eccleſiaſtique or ſecular: ſecular is militarie or ciuill, polemick or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick. The firſt of theſe (wee bleſſe God) wee haue had little practiſe of, ſo little, wee can ſcarce imagine there is ſuch a thing: but wee may haue: It is not good to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the knowledge of it, firſt; for theſe men, ſoldiers, and warriours deſpiſed in this dull and fuſty time of peace, if occaſion ſerued, would be as highly eſteemed, as now baſely, who are of ſo high and braue an order, that God himſelfe is ſaid to bee the ſoueraigne of their <pb n="6" facs="tcp:857:6"/>order: The Lord is a man of warre (ſaith
<hi>Dauid</hi>) the Lord of Hoaſts is his name; hee teaches my hands to warre and my fingers to fight: and as the motion from God, ſo the aſcent is by degrees, ranks they haue, and orders, Officers, sergeants, Lieftenants, Captaines, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronels, Generals, Admirals: of the height whereof iudge, but by that of <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ioab</hi> and his brethren: you are too mighty for mee, yee ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah,</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> offer to the Shunamite; wouldeſt thou be ſpoken for to the King or to the Captaine of the hoaſt, as (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily) the ſecond perſon in the Kingdome. Now the end of armes is peace, the Ciuile Magiſtrate alſo (I meane ſubordinate, for of regall power the ſupreame on earth I ſpeake not now) is in high place; ſuch are the nerues and glory of a Kingdome, therefore Chronicled in the dayes of
<hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> and their offices regiſtred; ſuch &amp; ſuch were Chancellors and Recorders, ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the tribute, ſuch Iudges and Rulers. And in this ranke wee ſee and know a diuerſity of order, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of dignity, and all from God, <hi>a Deo ordinate,</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ordained by him; And as <hi>Salomon</hi> calls mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, <hi>Pro.</hi> 2. the Couenant of God, <hi>propter eximiam ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitatem;</hi> ſo
<hi>Dauid</hi> the Seſſion of Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, <hi>coetum Dei,</hi> as approued of him and honoured with his preſence, in a ſpeciall manner, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82. He ſits, <hi>in medio corum, 2. Chron.</hi> 19. But as the wilde and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Anabaptiſt would deſtroy all Magiſtracie from the libertie of the Goſpell; ſo there want not ſome ſuch froward diſputers (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of) men of peruerſe minds, that reaſon from the old Teſtament, that ſinne firſt brought in ſeruitude, or elſe God had made no ſubiection: It is true indeed that the ſinne of
<hi>Cham</hi> occaſioned his ſlauery, <hi>A ſeruant of ſeruants ſhalt thou bee, Gen.</hi> 9 But yet in pureſt nature, euen in the ſtate of innocencie there was a ſuperioritie, not onely in man ouer the creatures, but coniugall in the husband ouer the wife, in which eſtate had children beene borne, <pb n="7" facs="tcp:857:6"/>there would euen in the law of nature haue ſprung vp, <hi>patria poteſtas,</hi> a fatherly power, which in time muſt needs haue riſen to <hi>regia,</hi> or the ſame that <hi>regia</hi> is. And of this motion to and promotion, which comes from the Lord, comes alſo the right end ſet downe by saint <hi>Paul, That we vnder them may lead a quiet &amp; a peaceable life, in, &amp;c.</hi> Where peace may bee oppoſed to tumult, ſtrife, and priuate reuenge. For firſt, if we had not theſe lawfull aſſemblies, but that <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his fellow hammer heads might ruſh into the halls and ſeates of iudgement, what would they doe? why ſhout they would and teare the ayre with noyſes, and ſo part a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine before they knew why they were come together: and ſecondly, where would contention ſtop her courſe, did not the lawes confine vs, and (as God giues a law to the Sea) bound vs in, with a decree of, Hitherto ſhalt thou come and no further? And laſt of all would the Rorers of the Age, and Bretheren of the Sword bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, either by Gods prohibition (the God of peace) or the Kings Proclamation (a King of peace) were it not for <hi>Iudex &amp; vindex,</hi> the Iudge and the auenger of blood, who is appointed betwixt plea and plea, betwixt blood and bloud, <hi>Deutr.</hi> 17. that theſe vnruly and bloudy people may heare, and feare, and doe no more preſumptuouſly. I named Eccleſiaſtique, and will but name it, which together with the ciuill meete and are vnited vnder regall and ſoueraigne maieſty; as all the coniugations of ſinewes in the naturall body runne vp to the head: which is enough to ioyne and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine thoſe two ſtates and powers with the heauenly maſticke of true charitie. For as the vaile of the temple rending preſaged the ruine of the whole; ſo if theſe two flye off and fall to maligne, and ſeeke to conſume each other, it is no good <hi>Omen</hi> to the whole frame: It ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me only to remember, that <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> were bretheren, and to ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> with <hi>Dauids Ecce, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, how good it is for bretheren to dwell together in vnitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:857:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note>There is vſe to be made of this too for ſubiects, which is obedience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The glory of rule to Princes and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates (ſayes hee in <hi>Tacitus</hi>) the glory of obedience God hath giuen to the ſubiect; which muſt be yeelded both to the good and ill, either actiue or paſſiue, to the good as cauſes, to the wicked rulers as occaſions of our benefit; the good are nurſes, the ill in ſtead of temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, which muſt be endured as we endure drought and dearth, &amp; other things from heauen; And both the rule &amp; the reaſon is from God. <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect, &amp;c.</hi> for there is no power but of God, and powers that bee are by him ordered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond concluſion from this firſt perſon is, that high ones are ſometimes oppreſſors, &amp; here if I would ſpeake of wealth, it were eaſie to ſhew that ſuch do fall into temptation and noyſome luſts, and this among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but I meddle onely with honour and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of that wee may ſay, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> (in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe) <hi>The Princes and Rulers haue beene chiefe in this treſpaſſe. Nehem.</hi> 9.2. <hi>They bee fat kine of Baſhan fatted in the mountaines, that oppreſſe the poore and oruſh the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, Amos</hi>
4.1. High place being like high knowledge. This made Angels &amp; man ſcorne Gods direction that makes vs deſpiſe his dominion; then we haue no Lord wee know him not, <hi>What Lord ſhall controule vs,</hi> ſay they in the
<hi>Pſalme,</hi> and they are oppreſſors that ſo ſay: Then breake his bonds and caſt his yoake from vs: wee are Lawmakers then our ſelues, and our will ſhall be a Law, or we can do miſchiefe and the Law ſhall defend it. <hi>Ex plebiſcitis, &amp; Senatus conſultis, ſcelera exercentur.</hi> They becomming actors that ſhould bee reformers; it is the miſerie of the weakeſt and loweſt things to bee oppreſt by the higher: The earth as loweſt of all, is therefore blaſted from heauen, burnt with fire, colickt and pincht with winde, ouerflow'd and waſted with water, her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and her belly plowed and ript vp by her owne Children, who are but euen althought higher than ſhee, <pb n="9" facs="tcp:857:7"/>For duſt they are, and to duſt they returne; If the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Pitcher will venture the ſtreame along with the braſſe-pot, it is ſure to be knockt; The ſhrub that grows vnder the Oake is beaten bare with dropping on; what poore beaſts ſoeuer chance to come neare the lyon, though but in viſitation, the Foxe can ſpie
<hi>Vestigia nulla retrorſum;</hi> It is ſo with oppreſſors, they are neuer high enough, till others be vnder their feete, and by a cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſening argument, then pride themſelues as higheſt, when they haue made others loweſt.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Rhehoboam</hi> be an example. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.11. Before he was well warme in the Kingdome, he begins to ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, and ſhake vp the ſubiect: They come with pittifully complaining of the yoke made grieuous by his Father, and would haue him mend it; Come, come, (ſayes he) my Father? my Father was not ſo wiſe as he might haue beene. He did indeed but piddle, and trifle with you, I tell you my little finger ſhall be heauier than my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loines: Hee preſſed you indeed, but I will adde to it: adde what? What is more then preſſing? Why oppreſſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is preſſing with a vengeance: He cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed you with whips, but I will ſting you with Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Ther's a Gallant; ther's a firker indeed: Take heed you come not in his fingring. And doe we want expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the like? And that we may preſerue the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie of the Text, contenting our ſelues with Countrie and home examples, for ſo it is. If in a Countrie thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poore, &amp;c. Take one of theſe things that Fortune lifts vp, when ſhee is pleaſed to ieſt, and to make ſport in the world; a young heyre of the Countrie, ſuppoſe young <hi>Nymrod,</hi> of the race of the Gyants, comes to an eſtare of many thouſands, <hi>&amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento turbinis exit. Marcus Dama</hi> is incontinently knighted (as that is a thing of nought) Sir <hi>Rhehoboam Nymrod;</hi> what will he doe now? why? bluſter &amp; breake in vpon the poore tenants, downe they goe before this golden Calle, and worſhip him all ouer; Now adde to <pb n="10" facs="tcp:857:8"/>this meaſure of Altitude, a Cubite of Iuſticeſhip, and on that a <hi>Quorum; quantum vertice in aur as, tantum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice in Tartara,</hi> ſaid
<hi>Virgill</hi> of a Tree; and it is true of ſuch blocks as he; The higher in dignitie, the deeper in crueltic. And as <hi>Philoctes Coous</hi> is ſayd (being madd) to haue made him ſhooes of Lead, for feare the Wind ſhould blow him away; ſo he imagines his honor would evaporate vnſeene, if his power were vnfelt, he will tread vpon the poore: and as if he had leaden feet indeed, or feete like that Image in <hi>Daniel,</hi> halfe clay, halfe iron, nay, as if he had mill-ſtones in's feete, ſo hee will grind the faces of the poore, and tread them as <hi>Dauid</hi> trod his enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.</note> that is, flat, <hi>as myre in the ſtreets.</hi> Entring like a tempeſt, or a whirlewind, that leaues nought behinde it, nothing ſtands that is mankinde about him; his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie are
<hi>oues &amp; Boues, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note>But to diſpatch him out of the way, wee ſhall heare more of him, and his fellows, in Gods particular regard: till then, all the vſe wee can make of him is to ſhew the daunger of high place and authoritie; <hi>attendo celfitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; ê vicino periculum reformide,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Bernard</hi> to his <hi>Eugenius</hi>) the danger of falling into grieuous ſinnes, and this among, and aboue the reſt; For this is <hi>Salomons</hi> verdict, at leaſt, ſuch are returned as principall here, <hi>Alis oppreſſores.</hi> The high ones are oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Doctrine.</note>The third concluſion from the chiefe perſon here is, the triall of a Title, which is giuen God;
<hi>Altiſſimus,</hi> the Higheſt. The ſchoole makes three degrees of percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, both in nature, and ſcripture. Firſt, <hi>Negatie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, remotionis;</hi> He is not the Sunne, Moone not finite, mutable: Secondly,
<hi>Perfectionis, affirmationis,</hi> when what is moſt excellent in things create, wee applie to God by way of Analogie and reſemblance: So wee call him iuſt, mercifull, high, glorious: Thirdly, of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or ſuper-heminence, as this here implies. A title therefore ſutable to his nature, for to ſeeke him among the higheſt things, we know is ridiculous; to pin or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine <pb n="11" facs="tcp:857:8"/>him there impious; <hi>vltra, vltra quaerendus,</hi> ſtill aboue and beyond all we muſt enquire for him, (ſayes <hi>Bernard.</hi>) And as ſutable, ſo there is none of his titles more auncient; ſo ſoone (I thinke) as we find mention of any height amongſt men, regall, or ſacerdotall, as hoth are referred to him, ſo with this title annext, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14 <hi>Melchizedek</hi> king of
<hi>Salem,</hi> and prieſt of the moſt high God. It is held throughout the old Teſtament, and not left of in the new. So <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> is called the Prophet of the higheſt: and <hi>Luke</hi> 6.35. <hi>Doe good, &amp;c. and ſo be Children of the higheſt:</hi> So that as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of his greatneſſe: <hi>God is great, and there is no end of his greatneſſe;</hi> So he is high too, and no end of his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. We haue thoſe on earth that are to day high, to morrow low as the graue, and therefore though men haue, and doe weare this title of moſt high, yet God weares it with a difference (ſayes the Prophet.) <hi>But thou O Lord art most high for euermore.</hi> Pſal. 92.8. And as it belongs to him for euer, ſo to euery perſon in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, to the Father firſt, acknowledged both by the powers of heauen and hell: In <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32. A celeſtiall Angell teſtifies of Chriſt, <hi>He ſhall be called ſonne of the higheſt:</hi> and in <hi>Luke</hi> 8.28. the Confeſſion of a ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall: <hi>Ieſus thouſonne of the moſt high God.</hi> So the ſonne himſelfe is ſtyled, (the ſame S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſtill 1.78.) <hi>Oriens ex alto, the day ſpring from on high.</hi> And in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.21. He is ſayd to ſit at his Fathers right hand, farre aboue all principalities and powers, hauing put all things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feete, and giuen him to be head ouer all things: So the holy Ghoſt is not onely called <hi>virtus ex alto, power from on high, Luk.</hi> 24.49. but of him ſayd; <hi>The power of the moſt high ſhall ouer-ſhadow thee. Luke</hi> 1.35. In ſo much that God himſelfe ſeemes to receiue delight and complacencie in this title; for whether men prayſe him on earth, it muſt be with an <hi>Hoſanna</hi> in the higheſt, or Angels and Hoſts from heauen, it muſt hee with a
<hi>Gloria Deo in excelſis, Glorie to God in the highest.</hi> Now
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:857:9"/>this title is applied to God, either in reſpect of his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or his attributes and diuine vertuer. Firſt in eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and nature he is <hi>Altiſſimus,</hi> among the cauſes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, exemplarie, finall, he in all theſe hath the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, as <hi>primum, principium,</hi> and <hi>vltimus finis.</hi> In puritie of nature, water aboue earth, aire aboue water, then fire, then light, and he <hi>Pater luminum, the Father of lights.</hi> Beaſts aboue plants, men aboue beaſts, aboue men, Angels and ſpirits, and he <hi>Pater ſpirituum, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpirits.</hi> In ſublimitie of nature, there being in him, the perfection of all his creatures, and that in a moſt eminent, and vnſpeakeable degree. So that none is Higheſt but he onely; nay, none like the Higheſt; He that ſaid, he would be, fell the loweſt; <hi>I ſaw Satan fall from heauen like lightning.</hi> As thus in eſſence, ſo laſt of all in Diuine vertue. Now there is incident to God none of thoſevertues, which ſuppoſe imperfection, as Faith, Hope, &amp;c. But ſuch as theſe; mercy, bountie, power, iuſtice, wiſedome, holineſſe: and in all theſe is GOD ſuperlatiue, nay, infinitely aboue all degrees of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon: we may chooſe to ſhew it in theſe foure for all the reſt, mercie, wiſedome, iuſtice, power.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> His mercie firſt is higheſt ouer all his workes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. For his power made nothing, but what his mercy mooued him to; of an vnknowne height it is then, as appeares by
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.11. <hi>As high as heauen is ouer the earth; for it is ſtabliſhed in the heauens. Pſal.</hi> 88. <hi>and the earth is full of his mercie. Pſal.</hi> 32. In both places hee is <hi>Pater miſericordiarum, a father of mercies.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording whereto the Church prayes; <hi>O God whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and propertie is to haue mercie, &amp;c.</hi> For if we inquire a reaſon of his mercy at large to all his creatures; to men as his image, to good men as his ſonnes; what can bee returned but
<hi>ô altitudo! O the height of the exceeding ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercie!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, his wiſedome is another <hi>ô altitudo! Rom.</hi> 11. Mans knowledge is farre aboue the beaſts, <hi>in quibus non <pb n="13" facs="tcp:857:9"/>eſt intellectus.</hi> But we come to no height, no perfection, <hi>in enigmate,</hi> in part and but darkely, like the Foxe lick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Viall, when he could not come at the liquor it ſelfe: And if yet euen from men, wee ſee ſo manie wiſe lawes of Princes, and Bookes of Councellors and Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in which there is extant a ſtrange light of humane. reaſon, what ſhall we thinke of the Higheſt, in whom is the higheſt law, out of which as out of a fountaine theſe are drawne, and thither as waters to the Sea returned. For there is one Law-giuer, and one Iudge,
<hi>Iam.</hi> 1. By whoſe onely wiſedome it is that Kings doe raigne, and Princes decree Iuſtice. <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. What euer the Creature hath, is a deriuatiue from that Primitue, as Art is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighed (ſayes <hi>Aquinas</hi>) from the mind of the Artizan into his workemanſhip. So that this whole Vniuerſitie of Gods worke is (as it were) a certaine common place of wiſedome: But that poore deale whereof men are capable, is receiued in long time, and but by drops; by many acts we vnderſtand one thing, hee in one act all; diſtinctly: they are naked and bare in his ſight, with their ſubſtances, formes, differences; wee read of wiſe men from the Eaſt, and of the high wiſedome of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> excelling all the Eaſt, but nor he, nor thoſe three attained to the firſt three; not to <hi>Alti</hi> here, in the end of this verſe. Downe then with all humane preſumption, and aſcribe vnto the Lord (as the glory) ſo the wiſe dome due vnto his name, for as his name is here, ſo is his wiſedome, higher than the higheſt. There is no Iudge aboue God, nor none that hath vnderſtanding like the higheſt. 2. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 7.19.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> We come to his Iuſtice and Power, of which it is here eſpecially vnderſtood, that he is <hi>Altiſſimus.</hi> His Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice firſt, ſo high that he is ſayd to be Iudge alone; and this height of Iuſtice is beſt diſcerned by the armes, or top branches;
<hi>Proemium &amp; poena,</hi> Reward and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whoſoeuer ſhall but regard thoſe foure conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Hell torments, for varietie the moſt, for their <pb n="14" facs="tcp:857:10"/>greatneſſe inſufferable, for puritie vnmixt with the leaſt allay of comfort, or hope of mitigation, for their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance euerlaſting, will eaſily diſcouer in them Gods Iuſtice to be higheſt. And contrary for reward it excels all, a good meaſure, preſſed downe, yet running ouer: <hi>Great is your reward in Heauen.</hi> Earthly Monarches thinke they goe far, when they ſpeake like <hi>Herod,</hi> euen to the halfe of my Kingdome: And what a poore thing is that? Not an inch in the mapp, and in the forme of the Heauens nothing. The goodly houſes they beſtow, are but as Childrens, Kings halls, made of ſhells and duſt, and what pleaſures the Courts of Princes can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</note> let <hi>Moſes</hi> refuſall tell vs;
<hi>pleaſures of ſin,</hi> common to vs with beaſts, <hi>and but for a ſeaſon,</hi> for a moment. But whom God exalts and aduances, hee rewardes with his owne kingdome, a kingdome of glory; his owne cittie, a cittie of pure gold, in that manſion to remaine with him, at the ſame Table, and yet higher, to ſit with him vpon the ſame throne. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3. This is more then euer was: <hi>Omnis poteſtas impatiens conſortis.</hi> And
<hi>Pharoah</hi> to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his prime fauorite,<note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
               <hi>onely in the throne I will be aboue thee.</hi> What might be added of the high nature of thoſe ioyes, which the Angels enioying doe adore; and of their eternitie? <hi>At his right hand are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> To giue vs heauen (if wee could doe his Law) were Iuſtice high enough, though but for one inſtant of time, but when it is added, <hi>For euermore,</hi> it is <hi>Iuſtitia in exceſſu, &amp; in excelſo</hi> too. T'is Iuſtice at the Higheſt.</p>
            <p>And finally, no leſſe admirable is the Power of God, which is ſo high in him (ſayes <hi>Beza</hi>) it makes him euer Agent,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and neuer Patient, and that can neuer ceaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame it is.
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> would proue the Popes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, by his twelue great names giuen him by his Paraſites, more eaſie were it from Scripture, recounting the glorious names of God, as alſo from his miracles to draw vp this Power to a ſupreame head. But it is a bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten way, and a ſubiect ſo full, that who euer handles it, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:857:10"/>cannot chooſe but handle it well. I will onely inſtance in that height of Power, which is expreſt, and prooued by place. Power terreſtriall is declared by aſcending to thrones, and if exaltation be meaſured ſo, then the Lord alone (as
<hi>Eſay</hi> ſayes) ſhall be exalted; For hee dwells, (ſayes
<hi>Eſdras</hi>) aboue the Aire, <hi>ſuper altitudinem aëris.</hi> 2.
<hi>Eſ.</hi> 6. Nay, <hi>ſuper altitudinem coelorum,</hi> a ſecond
<hi>ſuper,</hi> aboue the height of the heauens. 2. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 4. That is a maine height. For who can find out the height of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? (ſayes
<hi>Syracides</hi>) the pride of the height, as hee termes it, <hi>Ecclus</hi>
43. I but there is another <hi>ſuper</hi> yet, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the heauens, and the heauens of heauens. What? aboue all? I farre (ſayes the Apoſtle) gone vp on high farre aboue all heauens, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.10. The Queene of
<hi>Sheba</hi> viewing the high throne of <hi>Salomon,</hi> of which the Text ſayes, <hi>There was none like it in any kingdome.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi>
10.20. and obſeruing all his royaltie: <hi>Non habebat vltra ſpiritum;</hi> ſhee was aſtoniſhed. But an higher than <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is here; For
<hi>Salomon</hi> in all his royaltie was not clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed like the <hi>Lillit</hi> of the field, much leſſe like the Lord of Heauen, who dwells in light inacceſſible, and cloths himſelfe with light as with a garment. As
<hi>Salomon</hi> had no ſuch roabe, ſo no throne like Gods: For he prepares his throne in Heauen, (ſayes the <hi>Pſalme</hi>) <hi>Solium excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> a throne high, and lift vp, <hi>Eſay</hi> 6. a glorious high throne ſayes <hi>Ieremie,</hi> 17.12. Before which throne all thrones are caſt downe (ſayes <hi>Daniel</hi>) for it is a fire flaming aloft, and towring vp higher than the higheſt. Now as the throne, ſo is the Power of God, that the embleme of this. And therefore King <hi>Dauid</hi> will not repent his kneeling to God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. For (as he adds) <hi>the Lord is a great God, and a great King aboue all Gods:</hi> Nor will <hi>Salomon</hi> for all his owne highneſſe, rob God of his honour, but ſtand to the title, which he hath giuen him here: It is no more than right. He is a King, euen <hi>Rex regum, a king ouer all kings,</hi> and higher than the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt:
<hi>Moſt high aboue all the earth, and much exalted aboue all Gods.</hi> Pſal. 97.9.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:857:11"/>
            <p>But of what vſe is this Title for vs?<note place="margin">Vſes.</note> of manifold vſe: We may draw all to <hi>Timor &amp; Amor,</hi> Feare and Loue. Firſt, Feare, and that firſt in geſture, when wee preſent our ſelues before him. It is exacted by himſelfe. We may beleeue him when he ſweares it: I haue ſworne by my ſelfe (ſayes the Lord) <hi>that euery knee ſhall bow to me.</hi> Repeated in <hi>Rom.</hi>
14.11. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.23. And hee giues vs ſuch examples as we cannot refuſe. Chriſt Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who beſt knew this height, &amp; the infinite diſtance betwixt the Creator and the creature as hee was moſt humbled in ſoule, ſo he profeſt it, in lifting vp his eyes to Heauen, in prayer, in kneeling, falling on his face. The glorious Angels adore with couering their faces, and falling downe before him. The Church begins her
<hi>Lyturgie</hi> with that inuitement; <hi>O come, let vs worſhip, and fall downe, and kneele before the Lord</hi> And yet I know not how it comes to paſſe, we ſeeme (many of vs) aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of doing this reuerence to God.
<hi>Hic homo erubeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit timere Caeſarem</hi> (ſaid <hi>Macaenas:</hi>) So rude is our beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and ſuch a ſacrifice of fooles we offer him, as if we neither thought vpon our owne condition, which is but doſt and aſhes, with one blaſt diſperſt paſt gathering vp againe; nor remembred him to be our God, for then we would not ſtand like Elephants, or ſtonie Pillars in his Temple; but proſtrate our ſelues, and thinke no abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment too much, not the loweſt, being done to him that is the Higheſt. So in our tongues (ſecondly) forbearing that ſawcineſſe, and familiaritie ſome vſe in Prayer; wherein as the heart muſt be <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo the lungs would be <hi>Feare,</hi> leaſt it catch an heate. So coole a forme is that of holy Church: <hi>Graunt vs O Lord thoſe things which for our vnworthineſſe, we dare not preſume to aske.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (ſayes
<hi>Salomon</hi>) God is in Heauen, and thou on the earth; Let thy words be warie, and few. The ſame feare ſhould poſſeſſe vs when we ſpeake of, or ſweare by his name, not vainely, falſely; For holy and reuerend is his name.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:857:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Amor,</hi> Loue: And this is natiue and radicall in the very temper of ourſoules, and as a ſparke would breake to flame, but that the world and the Diuell choake and keepe it downe, and this fraile corruptible maſſe weighs downe the immortall ſpirit: for theſe two are contrary one to another: The bodie of the earth, carthie, but the ſoule from heauen, heauenly, tho forced like the Sunbeames to conuerſe with filth and doſt, yet <hi>haeret o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginiſuae;</hi> cleaues ſtill in affection to God, and hath reſtleſſe motions of deſire to returne to him that made it, but clogd with ſinne and feebled in all her powers, ſhee muſt begge and wait now a ſuperinduction of <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that ſo being ſtabliſhed in faith and rooted in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and borne vp by the aſſiſtance of Gods ſpirit, as by the wings of a Doue ſhe may flye vnto her reſt.</p>
            <p>This is exemplarie in holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe heart once touched with theſe diuine graces, he lifts vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his eies and hands, and heart, and voyce. O Lord, whom haue I in heauen but thee? or whom doe I deſire in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thee? As the Hart after the riuers, as the thirſty drye ground after ſhewres, ſo longs, pants, gaſps my ſoule after the liuing God. So will the heart of euery man that is like him, a man after Gods owne heart, make him his chiefe truſt, and marke of higheſt regard; for he that loues any thing better then mee, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of mee (ſayes Chriſt) hee is higheſt, and will haue the higheſt place in our affection, and hath therefore made it his firſt and great commandement. Loue the Lord thy God with all thy minde and might, and loue him aboue all things: They were ſtonie hearted Iewes that cryed, wee will not haue him rule ouer vs, not rule, then nothing: if hee may not bee the head ſtone, hee will not lye in any part of the building: and if wee ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to build without him, wo be to our foundation. Let valabour then to lift vp our heart, together with our hands vnto God in the heauens: Let vs call daily for his grace, and crye vnto him to draw vs after him, and <pb n="18" facs="tcp:857:12"/>hee hath promiſed to heare from his holy place, and ſend downe his hand from aboue, to mount vs vpon thoſe bleſſed ſtayres of iuſtification, ſanctification, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification; and then wee are where wee would be, with him <hi>that is higher then the higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>action</hi> heere referred to God is
<hi>regarding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> an action ſutable to the title. High places and noble acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould goe together: God is not then ſuch a God as <hi>Eliah</hi> makes <hi>Baal,</hi> perhaps hee ſleepes, no hee regards. Firſt generally all things: For in him they liue, moue, are: and as the eyes of all things look vp towards him, ſo his downe on all, in heauen, earth, vnder the earth: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> His prouidence extending it ſelfe like that tree in <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. from one end of heauen to another; whoſe branches reach out ſhade and ſuſtenance to all thoſe creatures reckoned vp in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104. For as the ſoule minds all the bodies actions, and the Sun penetrates all corners, ſo this true ſoule of the world and this Sunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but with a remarkable difference (ſayes Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) he does it without varrying or ſhadow of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnmoued, euer the ſame, hee ſits in midſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; and yet they bee the eyes of the Lord that runne too and fro through the whole earth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.10. raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning aboue, and yet containing all below, compaſſing all about and yet piercing all within: and what is yet more maruellous, this generall <hi>regard</hi> and diſcerning of
<hi>Gods,</hi> to extend euen to all things: al the ſtars, al the ſons of men, all the Cattell on 10000. hills, all thoſe number les ſhoales of fiſhes in the ſeas, all foules of the ayre, euen to ſeueralls &amp; minuities: the little ſparrowes, not one of them is forgotten, all the miſeries of all his ſeruants, all their teares in his bottle, in Man alone to <hi>regard</hi> all the members of his body, <hi>greſſus</hi> (ſayes
<hi>Dauid</hi>) the ſteps of his feete, <hi>capillos</hi> (ſayes our Sauiour) hayres on his head, all the ſinnes of his ſoule, and all in order, all our workes, not a word in our tongue, nay, in our heart, (from whence imaginations riſe as faſt as ſparks from <pb n="19" facs="tcp:857:12"/>a furnace) not a thought, but our heauenly father, who ſees in ſecret, ſees it though nere ſo ſecret; nay long be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore either birth or conception: and as hee calls, ſo hee knowes too and regards the things that are not as if they were. O Lord our gouernour, how excellent is thy name, for it is higher than the higheſt, &amp; how excellent is thy knowledge in all the world, for there is nothing, was, nor can, nor ſhal be nothing but thou O Lord knoweſt it altogether.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now this generall runnes into two ſpeciall
<hi>reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> or obſeruats, the one of mercy ouer the good, and the other of iuſtice ouer the wicked: <hi>His eyes behold, Pſ.</hi> 11. <hi>and his eyelids trye the children of men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but with a different regard: hee watches ouer all, but ouer ſome for preſeruation, ouer others for deſtruction: <hi>Ier.</hi> 31 and in <hi>Ier.</hi> 44. hee calls it a watching for good, and a watching for ill: with the firſt hee daily watched ouer his owne Iſrael, in a cloud and fiery pillar, but through them both it is ſaid hee looked on the hoaſt of Aegypt and troubled it, <hi>Exod,</hi>
14.24. Tis true he delights moſt in the firſt of theſe watchings, and then his highneſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſt pleaſed, when ioind with a mercifull regard, when hee ſhewes vs the beauty of his holineſſe, &amp; cauſes the light of his countenance to ariſe: But if our ſinnes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke him to anger, he will ſuffer his diſpleaſure to ariſe, and tho wee be his owne people, tender as the apple of his eye, and his chiefe treaſure aboue all nations; yet then, as hee threatens Iſraell, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26 9. hee will ſet his face againſt vs, then (as <hi>Daniel</hi> hath it) he will watch vpon the euill and bring it vpon vs. So that it is a true title <hi>Seneca</hi> giues him, <hi>Deus bonorum, malorumque obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uator &amp; cuſtos.</hi> Our good and our euill,
<hi>Hee that is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the highest regardeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Laſtly, regards this particular ſin
<hi>Oppreſſion;</hi> the patient, firſt in mercie, and firſt of all as
<hi>pauperem,</hi> then (moſt of all) as <hi>pauperem preſſum,</hi> the poore oppreſſed: <hi>God regards the Poore:</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And the maieſty of the title <pb n="20" facs="tcp:857:13"/>prefixt, makes this action glorious: what hee? whoſe excellence hath no ſtint vpward, aboue the clouds, ſtarres, heauens of heauens, ſtill higher then the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, to looke downe <hi>de ſuper,</hi> ſo low: <hi>a ſolio, ad ſolum,</hi> from his throne of glory, <hi>in excelſis,</hi> to regard the cries of the poore,
<hi>de profundis?</hi> yet ſo it is, thou God ſeeſt mee (ſayes poore
<hi>Agar</hi>) <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. And the euer-bleſſed Virgin: <hi>Thou haſt regarded the low or poore eſtate of thy handmaid:</hi> And this ſeemes a kinde of ſtate in God, and then his highneſſe is in full Maieſty, when hee ſhewes his powerfull <hi>regard</hi> ouer the meaneſt, and the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed on earth, ſuch as men ſell for ſhooes and count not worth looking after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea God is expreſſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as if hee laboured for the aduancement of the Poore, and then moſt of all when they are moſt wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 113. hee is ſaid to lift at it, to raiſe the poore euen out of dung, to ſet him with Princes, &amp;c. It is a great mercy to behold an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble God, who being higheſt, yet bowes down himſelfe to regard the poore: but much more <hi>pauperem preſſum,</hi> the poore oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Pouerty is but a ſhallow plaſh of miſery, but Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion breaking in, raiſes it to a floud, euen a red ſea of bloudy cruelty, deepe and deadly: but then one deepe calls vpon another, and it ſeemes not to be in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God to withhold his mercifull
<hi>regard;</hi> as we ſee by viſiting his Iſraell in Aegypt, and by his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: <hi>Now for the ſighing of the needy and oppreſſion of poore, I will vp (ſaith the Lord) Pſal.</hi> 12.5. If once they come to the ſhadow of death, to bee faſt bound in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and iron, &amp; then crie to the Lord in their trouble, he deliuers them out of their diſtreſſe. One example, &amp; tis a full one indeed. <hi>Dauid</hi> in a caſe of oppreſſion he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes himſelfe (as his known &amp; only refuge) vnto God, &amp; calls him by this very name in the text,
<hi>Altiſſimus, Pſ.</hi> 56 2. <hi>Mine enemies</hi> (it is indeed <hi>my obſeruers</hi>) <hi>daily op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe me and would deuoure me. Be mercifull vnto mee, O Lord thou moſt high:</hi> though they be high ones and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:857:13"/>obſerue me watching ouer me for euill, doe thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard me for good, for thou art higher then they, &amp; thou beholdſt iniquity &amp; wrong, yea thou regardeſt the poor but much more <hi>pauperem preſſum,</hi> the poore oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> We come to the agent whom he regards in iuſtice, as <hi>altum</hi> firſt, &amp; then as <hi>altum oppreſſorem:</hi> firſt as high God ſees not as man ſees; man thinks high things beſt and braueſt <hi>ſtupet in titulis &amp; imaginibus:</hi> But that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> high amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men, is abomination to God. They that lookt into the book of nature, ſaw the lightening ſcorch the mountains moſt, &amp; <hi>Lucretius</hi> obſerued, that <hi>res abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta quedam</hi> (as he cals it) a certain hidden thing there was which did ſtil
<hi>proculcare</hi> kick down the higheſt things, <hi>&amp; Iudibrio ſibi habere,</hi> ſeem'd to take pleaſure in ſo doing. And in the book of Gods ſcripture wee ſee what deſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation he threatens oft, &amp; oft ſeems delighted to bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the high ones of the world: ſo he ſeems to triumph ouer the <hi>Amorite,</hi> whoſe height was as the Cedars; yet I deſtroid (ſaies he) his fruit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, &amp; his root fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be low: ſo he doth menace <hi>Edom,</hi> tho high rooſted &amp; neſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed among the ſtars, yet there &amp; thence will I fetch thee down (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Ie.</hi>
49.16. theſe do indeed eſcape all power on earth (perhaps) but cannot free the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being the quarrie of him which is the higheſt. The hearn &amp; vulture outflying both falcon &amp; Gyrfalcon, is by the Sacre ſeizd on in an inſtant, which foule (as the name imports) is made by all a
<hi>ſymbole</hi> &amp; <hi>hyeroglyphick</hi> of the Deity, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 6. <hi>That he will come horribly &amp; ſpeedily vpon the wicked gouernours, &amp; a ſharpe iudgement ſhall be to them in high places: for mercy will ſoone pardon the meaneſt, but mighty men ſhall be mightily tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> But all this is to bee vnderſtood of high ones that are wicked on whom as he looks in ſpeciall iuſtice, ſo particularly on <hi>altum oppreſſorem,</hi> the high Oppreſſor.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Why, oppreſſion ſeems no ſuch great matter: at ſea the great fiſh eat the ſmal, in the ayre &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth there be beaſts &amp; birds of prey, that liue <hi>per rapinam</hi> (here) by <pb n="22" facs="tcp:857:14"/>cauening: I but <hi>non ſic inter vos,</hi> it ſhal not be ſo amongſt your God had another care in making ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after his own image, &amp; in keeping him vſes a gard of Angels, gards &amp; regards him, <hi>regards</hi> (ſaies the Scripture) <hi>all his hones,</hi> &amp; therfore who euer ſhede mans bloud, this great <hi>regarder</hi> wil require it. I, his bloud; but oppreſſion is not murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: tis true, things may bee flead aliue with cunning handling, but as good take <hi>vit
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as <hi>victum,</hi> life as liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load; beſide, there is more in this ſin then is yet diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: for who is it that bleeds? <hi>Non cruer hic de ſtipito ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, Polydorus ego ſum;</hi> and doth not Chriſt Ieſus ſay the ſame, <hi>I am Ieſus of Nazareth whom you perſecute,</hi> ſo whom you oppreſs to; it ſhall come all to a reckoning: for inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as you haue done it to them, you haue done it to me: therfore he giueth vs <hi>caueats, Rob not the poore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is poor, neither oppreſs the afflicted in the gate:</hi> why? what wil he do? <hi>The Lord wil riſe vp an aduocate and plead their cauſe,</hi> in forma pauperis, <hi>and ſpoile the ſoule of thoſe that ſpoile him, Pr.</hi> 22.23. And as there an aduocate, ſo in
<hi>Malachy</hi> a witneſs too, &amp; a ſwift one comes in (belike) before he is cald or lookt for. And tis no dallying in this caſe, <hi>for their Redeemer is mighty</hi> (ſales <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>Pr.</hi> 23.11 <hi>And if I commit this ſin</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>he wil terrifie me &amp;</hi> (<hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of</hi> altiſſimus <hi>here</hi>) <hi>becauſe of his highnes I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure:</hi> So in <hi>Ier.</hi> 22. he frights
<hi>Iohoiakim</hi> that had liued by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oring like a Lyon, with the burial of an aſſe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drawn and caſt our, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, caſt out into vtter darknes, where for eating the poore &amp; not regarding his tears, he ſhall haue both weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: <hi>For ouer theſe terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ones on earth that watch for iniquitie, Eſa.</hi> 29. <hi>there is a terrible ſuperviſor aboue, who (without repentance) will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them to a terrible one below too, euen the King of terror who will ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rore them;</hi> for tis his propertie, (&amp; they do but learne of him to goe about like a roring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may deuoure. And this the Lord calls recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencing their own way, <hi>Deſtroying for deſtroying, Ezech.</hi> 22. <hi>vlt.</hi> And (that which is worthy our regard &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">1619.</note> now <pb n="23" facs="tcp:857:14"/>ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>able) ſo ſore an auenger is God of this ſin, that for it he threatens not the age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts only, but the whol land. In <hi>Am.</hi> 8. ſee what work the Lord ſwears he wil make there. <hi>he wil neuer forget it, he wil make it a bitter day; nay, the land ſhal tremble and riſe vp wholly as a floud, &amp; be drowned as in the floud of Egypt,</hi> which was a whole deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (indeed) for the text ſaies (i remember) <hi>there was not one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> left:</hi> ſo terribly doth the regard of his iuſtice fal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe 2. when ioin'd together,
<hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppreſſore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the high oppreſſor.</p>
            <p>He that in wiſe will conſider this. And the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is vſefull.<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to make vs take out <hi>Salomons</hi> leſſon of <hi>Nemixiris:</hi> Be not aſtoniſht, doe not wonder at the matter, that is, <hi>iſtem v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>em;</hi> at this will or purpoſe in God; for <hi>Iunius</hi> interpretation of the will or councell of wicked men is too cold, &amp; vnlikely. No: <hi>Salomon</hi> would not haue vs repine at Gods ordering the matter <hi>Nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiris.</hi> Where ſimply to wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der is not forbidden for hat's the ſeed of knowledge &amp; an impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of delight, which man may &amp; is invited to take in ſorveighing the workes of God. <hi>O conſider and behold!</hi> And cherefore the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers in their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, wherein they placed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d to take away this pleaſant admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and obſecuring the world, nor to hinder our liuely, actiue, &amp; vigorous conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of God, for it becomes not onely our religion, but diſcretion too, to mount our holieſt &amp; chaſteſt thoughts vnto him, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely aboue the higheſt endeuours of our imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but they taught the ſame that <hi>Salomon</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> here <hi>ne mireris not wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der with aſtoniſhment,</hi> which they could not vnderſtand of a profound careleſneſſe, for then women &amp; idle diſſolutes would doe it duly. But they meant a beauteous ſweet ſtate of the ſoule, by taking downe the ſails of vulgar opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which make men nice, &amp; ſoon diſquieted. So that in <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mireris</hi> here, 2 things onely ſeeme prohibited. 1. a diſtruſt of Gods prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; 2. vexing our ſelues about the execution of his Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is a torment, which is onely in men; Beaſts <pb n="24" facs="tcp:857:15"/>know it not; nor ſeeme they to know either God or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that practice it. Why? He regards (ſayes <hi>Salomon</hi>) he rules in heauen, in earth, &amp; in all deepe places, He is thy King, Thou muſt either endure his ſway, or get out of his dominion. It is a very good one, the <hi>Mexican</hi> ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to their infants new borne ô child thou art borne to ſuffer, ſuffer and hold thy peace. Doe not whine and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine as the vulgar ignorant at euery ſtorm or more or may the tumor of an earth quake or a water wrack, though a 1000. leagues off, and but in a ballade, drawes them together like Bees at ſound of a baſon, and holds them ſuſpended and aſtoniſht. The ſimple plow-man is afraid thoſe cowling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of heauen ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their duties do him, and is ready to brawle with God, for croſſing the contents of his Almanack, &amp; not ſending him drought and ſhowers at his pleaſure. But what ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe? we all labour of the ſame infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, no man thinkes ſufficiently, that he is but man, and but one: for euery man take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon him to be a publicke paedagogue, and would rule this world with a rod; and we are prone all to quarrell with God of careleſnes, or of preſumption, that would make a would, &amp; not geuen is better than he does. <hi>Foodmen I.</hi> (ſayes <hi>Salomon</hi>) doe not breake your ſoules with theſe imaginations; better deny him vtterly, than thinke ill, or idly of his prouidence; as it is better for a man to be rumor'd dead, than reported wicked; For he regards the world, &amp; that law which was the part
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne to make it, is the Card to guide it by; not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy wil or wiſedome happily, but
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Ep.</hi> 1.11 <hi>according to the councell of his owne will;</hi> and if it force thee to a ſtand to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider it, beware yes of murmuring either at his prouidence, or iuſtice, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the ſecond thing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> T'was a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der to <hi>Cato,</hi> that when <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tis</hi> did all againſt right and reaſon, he euer proſpered, but for the Common-wealth had no ſucceſſe: and it would make any man wonder indeed, nay, vexe with <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſee the wicked in no miſ-fortune, like other men, nay, like <pb n="25" facs="tcp:857:15"/>good men (oftentimes.) <hi>for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ny are the troubles of the righteous,</hi> and among thoſe many, this is a maine one,
<hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> which is able to make euen a wiſe man madd (ſayes
<hi>Salomon</hi>) to ſuffer it, and enough (as it ſeemes by this very Text) to ſtagger vs, beholding the poore op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and the oppreſſor goe free. I; but be not aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht (ſayes the <hi>Breacher.</hi>) <hi>Iudge nothing before the time</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle.) We cannot by one title, or by one word iudge of the maſons fabrique, or the Poets verſe; we muſt view the contexture, and heare all the ſyllables ſound. And ſhall wee thinke to take a true eſtimate of Gods iudgement (ſayes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <hi>Auſten</hi>) <hi>ante quam totus orde decurrat.</hi> Before the whole ſtreame and courſe thereof be runne out? There remaines mercy for the righteous, as ſure it is that a iudgement to come remaines for the wicked; and as if none were puniſhed here, none would beleeue our report, that,
<hi>The higheſt Regardeth;</hi> ſo if all here ſtriken, who would regard a iudgement to come?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, ſince God regards the poore oppreſſed, here is double conſolation for the poore, all poore, for it is no perſonall priuiledge this. They are Lampes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed in the opinion of the rich, but not in his, who is rich ouer all. He regards them, in mercy, and the rather for being poore, nay, the more poore, the more he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for thats true the t'other way too: that which is abomination to men, he that is higher than the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt regardeth. And of what can they deſpaire, who are thus highly regarded, by him who is able for earthly to giue treaſure in heauen? which nor defrauder, nor op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor can bereaue, for a ſmoakie cottage here, a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a 1000. ſtories high, <hi>not made with hands, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the heauens.</hi> Meane time, wanting mony they haue his louing fauour, which is aboue ſiluer and gold; in ſtead of corne, and wine, and oyle, he ſhewes them the light of his countenance, and in mercie regards them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, conſolation too for <hi>Panperem preſſum.</hi> What though oppreſt &amp; depreſt, euen as low as the dungeon, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:857:16"/>or the den, or the belly of the Whale or the bottome of the belly of hell (ſayes <hi>Sirach:</hi>) yet here are two words like a payre of heauenly pullies, able to fetch them vp, to an high &amp; liuely conſolution, <hi>Altiſſimus, obſervat. He that is higher than the highest regardeth.</hi> This then is, <hi>The poore Mans Appeale,</hi> ſo call this Text, when ſtung with thoſe fierie ſerpents, they may yet fixe their eye on this brazen ſerpent, that is lift vp higher than the higheſt, and yet from thence <hi>Regards</hi> and ſend downe that cheatful voice of the Prophet; <hi>The needy ſhall not alway be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.18.</note>
               <hi>the patient abiding of the poore ſhall not periſh for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſt vſe is of feare, to the <hi>High</hi> one firſt, and then the oppreſſor. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Let the high one of earth haue an awfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the higheſt regarding him, regarding all wicked ones in Iuſtice,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but wicked rulers in ſeueritie. And then let the oppreſſor feare, foure this curſed ſin even pidling oppreſſion, (which we count a pregnancie, and a verie fine qualitie,) defrauding and circumventing our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in barganing; for euer of ſuch things the Lord is the ave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. Much more let the high oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors feare that crying and bloudie ſin, who tho they can ſcape the iudgement of men, yet how will they preuent or eſcape <hi>ſuper
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inſpectorem,</hi> he that is in his holy watch tower aboue, and in whoſe ſight all thinge are naked &amp; manifeſt, &amp; whoſe vengeance is both ſuddaine &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull,
<hi>vno nutu,</hi> at one becke able to preſſe and cruſh, &amp; for euer periſh a whole world of oppreſſore, at the very blaſting of the breath of his diſpleaſures.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>And firſt doe you (moſt Reuerend Iudges) ſuffer the word of Exhortation: you ſee your calling is an high one, ſharing with God, in names of Lord &amp; Iudge: nay,
<hi>I haue ſaid you are Gods, and are all children of the moſt high. Be followers of God as deare children;</hi> follow him, tho <hi>non paſſibus aequis.</hi> For humane nature is not capable of perfect iuſtice, no more then of other things in their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; onely ſee that you bend your higheſt endeuors in imitation of the higheſt; not kept downe by the baſenes <pb n="27" facs="tcp:857:16"/>of the world, nor your ſweet and wholeſome acts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (like the Sun-beames in a burning glaſſe, bowd, &amp; contracted by paſſion or partiality, <hi>&amp; be merciful, as your heauenly father is merciful,</hi> ſans hope of earthly reward or ſting of vainglory: and being in the place of God, learn his action heere of
<hi>regarding,</hi> for this end ſits he in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and he hath not ſet you here to be <hi>regardleſſe,</hi> like <hi>Gallio, Act.</hi> 18. one that cared for nothing, as ſo many Scarcrowes in a garden of Cucumers; but to
<hi>regard</hi> the poor in mercy, &amp; the <hi>high Oppreſſor</hi> in iuſtice: &amp; ſay not you to him as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to old <hi>Iacob, not ſo, my father,</hi> reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather your hand (clean co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary) of iudgment to the <hi>poor,</hi> &amp; of fauor to the <hi>oppreſſor:</hi> but in mercy reſpect the poore &amp; needy, that are ſick and need your phyſick, not purges or lettings bloud with the whip, ſo much as your cordials of prouiſion, your gentle laxatiues, your bleſſed lenitiues &amp; reſtoratiues: And in juſtice regard their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, &amp; look that ſuch as ar the grand thieues ſit not neer you on the bench, while the petite ones plead at the bar for mercy. I know that ſimple people think you may do wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, but my prouocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tends no further then to vrge the execution of that lawful power, which to you throgh our excellent Soueraign is conuaid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him <hi>that is higher then the higheſt.</hi> And that therin you would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the oppreſſor, &amp; beware leſt (as the Apoſtle ſaies in another caſe) <hi>the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law,</hi> ſo theſe high ones do not ſtrengthen their hands in this ſin of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, either by the ſhelter or conniuence of the Law or Magiſtrate, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if you do not, <hi>he regards</hi> that is higher then they or you: and w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if you labour to do, by deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (as the Prophet ſpeaks) the gain of oppreſſion, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your hands fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking of bribes, ſtopping both eies and eares from ſeeing euill, or bearing bloud, then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards in mercy, &amp; <hi>great is your reward in heauen,</hi> for your defence ſhall be the munition of rocks, and you ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit <hi>loca altiſſima, the higheſt place, Eſ.</hi> 33.16. And this ſpeech to you (my gracious Lords) is but like a ſecond impulſion to a wheel already moud, and I admoniſhing to <pb n="28" facs="tcp:857:17"/>do what you ar obſerud to do already, do in my admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition bear along both praiſe &amp; approbation. Conſider then what I haue ſaid, <hi>and that Lord Iudge of heauen and earth,</hi> who is only wiſe, <hi>giue you vnderſtanding in all things.</hi> And next let vs learn to aply this text, we that ar now in his ſight, ſpeaking, hearing, for
<hi>he regards</hi> out inſtant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſees our reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, knows our thoughts. When we part from hence, the Text will follow vs, in our houſes, chambers, cloſets, his eye is euer on vs, let then the eyes of our ſoules be euer fixt on him, &amp; euer even in midſt of night &amp; ſilent darknes ſuppoſe our ſelues in a <hi>Theater</hi> ſince he ſees vs; &amp; euery where vpon our walls and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in our rings, and on our fore-heads, and in the palmes of our hands, ingraue this poſie, <hi>Altiſſimus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruat.</hi> Doe you in ſpeciall that are to attend the Courts of Iuſtice &amp; iudgement, Councellors in your pleas, and witneſſes in your depoſitions; Ere you ope your mouths hearken to the voice of <hi>Salomon</hi> here, nay, lend but an eare to the call of your owne conſciences, and they will preach this text vnto you; <hi>He that is higher then the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt regardeth.</hi> And you of the Iewry be not like thoſe Phyſitians, who vſe to erect a figure, by that minute, in which they are conſulted, and thereby giue their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For thats too vſuall with ordinary Iurors, to haue regard to certaine aſpects, and relations, and predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancies, and to giue verdicts according as they find Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors enclin'd. Their Landlord may chance to frowne elſe, and take away their leaſes, or caſt them out of their houſes: I, but <hi>Salomon</hi> tels vs of a ſuperior here far aboue all Lords, by Land or by Water, one that can depriue them of inheritance in the kingdome of Heauen, and able to caſt them both bodies &amp; ſoules into Hell: And therefore feare him; feare not their regarding, but hi-regarding;
<hi>His that is higher then the higheſt:</hi> To whom be prayſe and glory, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <q>Gloria Deo in Excelſis.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:857:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
